A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Democracy, Rights, and Justice Program, Vice President, Office Files of Maya Harris FA1456
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Democracy, Rights, and Justice Program, Vice President, Office Files of Maya Harris
1996-2005
Rockefeller Archive Center
Harris, Maya
Ford Foundation
FA1456
.71 Cubic Feet 1 LGL size Hollinger box and 1 Half-LGL size Hollinger box
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
This material was transferred to the RAC in 2018 by the Ford Foundation and was ingested by the RAC as Accession 2018:036.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation was chartered by Henry and Edsel Ford in 1936 "to receive and administer funds for scientific, educational and charitable purposes, all for the public welfare", and initially served the Ford family's charitable interests in the Detroit area. Following the deaths of Edsel Ford (1943) and Henry Ford (1947), the Foundation was propelled to the forefront of philanthropy as the largest American foundation in terms of both endowment and yearly expenditures, and with an international scope to its major program areas.
During the Foundation's first twenty years its major programs were in international economic development, primary and higher education, educational and public broadcasting, behavioral sciences, civil liberties, urban development, fine arts and the humanities. The Ford Foundation also partnered with the Rockefeller Foundation in supporting agricultural development in South America, Africa, and Southeast Asia. Since the 1970s, the Foundation has also pioneered programs in women's rights, energy policy, micro-financing in under-developed countries, establishing human rights groups, and improving international HIV/AIDS education.
Arrangement
Collection consists of one series. Files within that series are arranged alphabetically by title.
Original order was maintained during processing.
The collection arrangement is as follows:
Series 1. Peace and Social Justice Program, Vice President, Bradford K. Smith subject files, 1996-2005.
Biographical / Historical
Maya Harris served as Vice President of the Ford Foundation's Democracy, Rights and Justice Program between 2008 and 2013. In this position, she was responsible for grantmaking decisions regarding the promotion of greater democratic participation and the protection for human rights.
After leaving Ford in 2013, she continued pursuing her interests in politics and philanthropy. She worked as a Senior Advisor for Hillary Clinton's 2016 Presidential Campaign and joined the Arkus Foundation's Board of Directors in 2017. She is the sister of U.S. Senator Kamala Harris.
Scope and Contents
This collection holds the office files of Ford Foundation executive staff member Maya Harris. However, the records in the collection were not actually created by Harris. They all originate from the Office of Ford Foundation Peace and Social Justice Program Vice President Bradford K. Smith. Inventory information provided by Ford to the RAC described the materials as historical documents, suggesting that Harris had inherited Smith's files and that her Office absorbed those documents into its own records. Harris served as Vice President for Ford's Democracy, Rights, and Justice Program between 2008 and 2013. This program likely succeeded the Peace and Social Justice Program that Smith served. Future accessions may expand the collection so that it includes documents produced by Harris' Office.
Collection materials chiefly consist of correspondence, agendas, notes, grant recommendations, reports, and speech transcripts. They originate from between 1996 and 2005, all within the timeframe of Smith's tenure as Peace and Social Justice Program Vice President.
Ford Foundation; Civil rights; Discrimination in education; Democracy
- Peace and Social Justice Program, Vice President, Bradford K. Smith subject files, 1996-2005; 1; .71 Cubic Feet About 1 LGL size Hollinger box and 1 Half-LGL size Hollinger box
  Scope and Contents
  Series consists of the subject files of Ford Foundation Peace and Social Justice Program Vice President Bradford K. Smith. Smith's records likely became absorbed into the office files of Ford Democracy, Rights, and Justice Program Vice President Maya Harris through inheritance. The subject files are arranged alphabetically by title and many were created to document the Peace and Social Justice Program's work with a specific organization. There are also files containing organizational information such as staff members' biographies, and a file containing a group of transcripts of Smith's speeches at various meetings and events.
  Researchers will note that the series is comprised of only files starting with the letter S. Future accessions may expand the series so that it includes the missing subject files. However, there is a possibility that Harris' Office only inherited this small group of Smith's records.
  - Senior Directors' meetings with Vice Presidents, 1997-2003 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Palestinian Diaspora and Refugee Center (Shaml), 2004 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Swedish International Development Cooperation Agency (SIDA), 1999 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Sierra Club, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Simon Wiesenthal Center, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Smith, Bradford K. speeches, 1997-2003 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Soros Foundation, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
  - Southern Echo Inc., 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
  - Southern Education Foundation (SEF), 1997 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Space - Ford Foundation New York Office, 1996-2004 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Spanish note - Instituto de Estudios Peruanos (IEP), undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Social Science Research Council (SSRC), 2000 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Staff biographies, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Staff directory, 1996 September (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Stepan, Alfred, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 19)